[snorts]
>> War ravaging the East since 1937 and
Japan's [music] invasion of China
reached Europe on the 1st of September
1939 with Germany's invasion of Poland.
It became global on the 7th of December
1941 when Japanese aircraft attacked the
American naval base at Pearl Harbor.
It touched every continent
and lasted for 6 years.
It ended with a new weapon for a new
age.
This is the history [music] of the
greatest of all man-made events.
These men are part of that history.
They are eyewitnesses to the triumphs
and tragedies of the war wherever it was
fought.
Their testimony is part of the story of
how our world was made
by those who could pay
and those who could no longer meet
the price [music] of empire.
Both of the main Axis partners had
enjoyed extraordinary success with their
initial offensives. [music]
Germany in Central Europe, in Western
Europe, and in the invasion of the
Soviet Union.
Japan in the Pacific and in Burma,
Malaya, the Philippines, the Dutch East
Indies.
In 1943,
the complexion of the war changed.
By the turn of the year,
the Axis was on the defensive
everywhere.
Through 1944, in every theater of war,
Allied strength would grow in the East,
in the Soviet Union, and with the
opening of the second front.
The Allied bombing campaign against
Germany was relentless.
The dwindling stocks of the Luftwaffe,
which could have made a valuable
contribution on the Eastern Front, were
committed to the defense of German
cities and German industry,
as were many tens [music] of thousands
of military personnel.
For 6 months from September 1943 to the
last day of March 1944,
RAF and American bombers hammered German
targets.
From January, they were supported by
long-range fighter escorts as the
Mustang P-51B's came into service.
>> We flew at 30,000 ft with no heat in the
plane,
so it was really cold.
We had
a flight suit which looked like an
electric blanket with a plug at the
navel, which had a cord which we could
plug into the airplane, and it would
heat our suit,
which made it really comfortable. You
were okay.
>> Bomber Command continued its
concentration on the cities, encouraged
by the devastating raids that had
unleashed a firestorm on Hamburg,
killing more than 40,000. After Harris
turned to the capital in what became
known as the Battle of Berlin.
Though the Führer moved around Berlin
with the curtains drawn in his car so
that he would not have to see the damage
being done to his capital.
Extensive raids failed to [__] the
city.
>> By the time I got there, we had
something called G. I had a screen as
navigator in my part of the plane
where I could know exactly where I was.
If there was cloud cover, which there
usually was,
I would use that.
Otherwise, I just have to do dead
reckoning and try to recognize the the
drift.
>> Attacking military objectives was more
effective. Big Week in February, in
which the RAF and the US 8th and 15th
Air Forces dropped more than 15,000 tons
of [music] explosives
on aircraft and aircraft component
factories permanently injured the
Luftwaffe.
>> It's the spirit through the whole thing
was one of purpose.
The camaraderie was uh was excellent.
The acceptance of [music] losing a buddy
was excellent.
There was never
never a question of we shouldn't be
here, [music] we shouldn't be doing
this. Never by anyone.
>> It had become clear by the spring of
1944 that bombing
would not bring a population to its
knees and end the war. At the end of
March, Bomber Command had launched a
raid on Nuremberg in which 94 bombers
had been shot down
and 540 aircrew killed.
A greater death toll than Fighter
Command had suffered during the whole of
the Battle of Britain.
Nuremberg suffered minimal damage.
This was the raid that ended Arthur
Harris's Battle of Berlin.
1,000 aircraft had been lost. The
bombers were transferred [music] to
another task.
Their role in the invasion of Europe.
Across the globe, it was Allied [music]
forces that were facing invasion. The
Imperial Japanese Army renewed offensive
operations [music]
in Burma.
The Chinese were almost entirely
dependent for modern military equipment
on their allies.
In 1943, [music]
delivery of these supplies had been
drastically curtailed by the loss of
Burma and the Burma Road.
Efforts to construct [music] an
alternative route, the Ledo Road, folded
with the onset of the rains.
Allied plans for the resumption of
operations in 1944 were focused on
securing northern Burma so that the Ledo
Road could be completed.
The American General Joe Stilwell
commanding the Chinese Army in Burma
would move down from Ledo to the Burmese
border, then swing north building the
road as he went.
Meanwhile, British General Orde
Wingate's long-range [music]
group, the Chindits, would be airlifted
to the Irrawaddy cutting Japanese
[music] communications south of
Stilwell's force.
The Chinese Expeditionary [music]
Force operating out of China under
General Wei Lihuang would move against
the Japanese at Tengyueh, pushing the
56th Division towards Wingate.
That plan was initiated on February the
5th when the first elements of the
Chindits began their march from Ledo.
The following day, Japanese attacked.
The 55th Division moving north with the
intention of looping around and
attacking the 15th Indian Corps from the
rear.
As the Japanese offensive continued
attempts to gain an advantage in the
Burmese state of Arakan were called off.
The first time the British and Indian
troops had successfully repelled the
Japanese assault.
>> I was a forward scout.
About 100 yards up on the rest of me
section.
But you couldn't see anything.
All you could see was a mass of
greenery.
All of a sudden a shot rang out.
And I couldn't go forward then cuz I
didn't know how many Japs had.
It was just the one shot.
And I shot my air cool.
I was expecting to get shot carrying him
back.
I brought in the Americans
bombing the top of the hill where the
Japs was.
They pulled out during the night.
So, that was that.
>> In early March, the Chindits were flown
into the Kalewa Valley and for once an
airborne assault went well. An early
Japanese attempt to dislodge the force
was easily beaten off.
South of the Chindit landing zone, the
major part of the planned Japanese
offensive got underway a week earlier
than General Slim facing [music] the
attack had anticipated.
With the Japanese was a division of the
Indian National Army raised by the
Indian Independence leader Subhas
Chandra [music] Bose from Indian
prisoners of the Japanese.
These men, on crossing the Chindwin,
fell to their knees shouting Jai Hind,
Hail India.
The Japanese 33rd Division made progress
before turning north towards the Indian
20th and beginning to threaten Imphal.
The 20th was ordered to take a position
on the Imphal Road and hold it.
For 3 months of fierce fighting, they
held it.
>> Japanese objective became clear.
Kohima was a major [music] base. More
importantly, it was a railhead
and the gateway to Dimapur,
an enormous supply depot for the British
in India.
The Japanese 15th Division cut the
Imphal-Kohima road as they closed on
Kohima. The British command suffered
[music] a setback.
Orde Wingate was in the tradition of
eccentric British soldier mystics,
Gordon of Khartoum, Lawrence of Arabia,
was killed in a plane crash.
Command of the Chindits passed [music]
to Vinegar Joe Stilwell.
On April the 3rd, the Japanese 31st
Division closed on Kohima.
On that same day, one British infantry
battalion arrived to garrison the depot.
Besieged, they fought a desperate battle
for 2 weeks.
The perimeter contracted. More and more
of the village fell in fierce
hand-to-hand combat. At times, less than
15 m separated the front lines.
>> We existed on parachute supplies, you
know.
They dropped their rations by parachute,
which is Japs never had nothing like
that.
>> Japan's failure to supply and support
her troops [music] meant that 60% of
Japan's 1.74 million military losses
during the war were victims [music] of
starvation or disease.
On April the 18th, a Punjabi battalion
and a tank detachment succeeded in
breaking through to Kohima.
The defenders had suffered 300
casualties, but had held out.
>> The order was push the Japanese back.
They're not going to get any more
supplies.
They're not going to get any medicine.
So, they tried to push east.
The Japanese could not get the villagers
to give that much food.
So, the day sometimes forced the
villagers. So, the word went round.
Get out of the village if they come.
The Burmese will go after them now.
That you chaps, you bullied us now. They
started killing some of them.
So, they were in a terrible state.
>> On May the 11th, General Slim began his
offensive.
In mid-June, [music]
the Kohima-Imphal road was reopened.
>> The Japanese
They were never taken prisoner. They
generally killed themselves.
>> The India-Burma battlefield was not the
only scene of offensive action in the
Asia-Pacific theater during 1944.
The Marshalls and the Gilbert Islands
captured and secure, Allied planning
turned towards the Marianas and beyond
that, the Philippines.
The Japanese could read a map as well as
the Americans and they too identified
the strategic significance of the
Marianas.
They planned [music] to respond to the
expected American assault by deploying a
strong fleet in combination with
aircraft based on the Marianas. Together
the plan proposed, they would destroy
the American carrier force.
That carrier force [music] was the
largest naval force yet to assemble in
the Pacific.
Built around 15 carriers, it was
supported by the Fifth Fleet with seven
battleships and 21 cruisers.
And then there was the invasion fleet,
which was carrying four full divisions
of troops and included a further 12
escort carriers, five battleships and 11
cruisers.
Admiral Toyoda had command of the fleet
assembling to face the Americans and to
counter their massive armada, he had
five battleships and eight carriers.
>> June the 11th, the assault on the
Marianas began with a bombing attack on
the most northerly of the islands.
Taking it first would prevent
reinforcements coming from Japan.
The most northerly of the islands
[music]
was Saipan.
It had a garrison of 32,000.
The Saipan landings were strongly
opposed and casualties were high, in
part because the fleet and air cover had
to be withdrawn when the Japanese naval
[music] force was spotted and the navies
positioned themselves for the Battle of
the Philippine Sea.
On the 19th and 20th of June, 1944,
the largest carrier battle in history
was fought.
Japanese initiated action with the
launch of air strikes against the US
carriers,
but the incoming waves were plotted on
radar.
As a result, the Japanese lost [music]
219 aircraft,
the Americans 29.
On that first day,
two Japanese carriers were sunk by
submarines.
On the second day, the main US carrier
force, Admiral Marc Mitscher, attacked
the Japanese,
sinking one carrier and destroying 65
aircraft.
The Americans dubbed the action
the Great Marianas Turkey Shoot.
In the final tally, the Japanese had
lost three carriers and 480 aircraft.
The Americans had lost no ships and 29
aircraft.
The losses to material and more
significantly to trained air crew
permanently and fatally weakened Japan.
A novel solution to her shortage of
skilled pilots would be found and named
for the divine wind that had twice in
the 13th century destroyed Mongol
invasion fleets saving Japan.
That wind was called Kamikaze.
On the 6th of July, the commanders on
Saipan ordered a final suicide attack
and [music] then committed suicide.
The next day, their orders were
followed.
When the battle was over, 26,000
Japanese were dead.
>> [music]
>> American dead totaled 3,426.
>> We were off Saipan, we saw civilians
diving off the cliffs, committing
suicide with their children.
>> 10 days [music] after the fall of Saipan
under increasing criticism for the
conduct of the war, General Hideki Tojo
[music] resigned as Prime Minister.
Three days later, the first US Marine
Division landed on Guam.
On the 24th, [music] the 2nd and 4th
Marine divisions landed on Tinian.
Resistance there ended on August the 1st
and on Guam on the 10th.
Although the last Japanese soldier
[music]
was not to surrender until 1960.
>> We had Guam.
And I got a nice dose of malaria.
105 fever.
They treated me a little bit aboard
ship, but they sent me home.
Believe it or not,
I was sent home.
Only those that was in the service
knows that feeling.
Hear your name, pack up, you're going
home.
>> Japan [music] was losing the war.
In the European theater, Allied progress
in Italy was slow and costly. [music]
Having landed on the mainland in
September 1943,
forces had moved north towards Rome and
the first of the German defensive
positions, [music]
the Gustav Line.
American divisions moved along the
Mediterranean coast from Salerno and
through Naples, and the British 8th Army
moved to link up with commandos who had
landed at Termoli on the Adriatic coast.
>> [music]
>> From early November, the Allies faced a
formidable opponent.
Albert Kesselring.
>> At the end of November, Montgomery
launched the 8th Army at the Gustav Line
and breached the defenses in the east.
But at the beginning of 1944, both
Eisenhower, Supreme Allied Commander,
and Montgomery were withdrawn from Italy
to concentrate on planning the invasion
of Europe.
Also in January of 1944, and despite
losses of 4 and 1/2 million, the German
armed forces reached their greatest
strength.
9 and 1/2 million under arms.
Although the numbers may misrepresent
the quality of those now conscripted to
fight,
the Wehrmacht that faced Mark Clark's US
5th Army on the western end of the
Gustav Line remained a formidable enemy.
January 22nd throughout flanked the
defensive position.
Operation Shingle landed the US 3rd and
British 1st Divisions behind the line at
a place called Anzio.
It was to become briefly the world's
fourth busiest port.
A strong beachhead was established 24 km
wide and 12 deep, but by then,
Kesselring [music] had ordered
reinforcements into the area and six
divisions had moved up.
In mid-February, the Americans began
their assault [music] on Gustav,
attempting the breakthrough that would
allow them to link up with forces
advancing from the Anzio beachhead.
Within a week, the American commander at
Anzio had been replaced, a punishment
for his lack of progress.
Germans continued their pressure on
Anzio in Operation Fish Fang, catfish,
and it was only Allied air supremacy
that kept them at bay.
Assault on the Gustav Line had meanwhile
been held up at a place called Monte
Cassino.
From February the 2nd to May the 17th,
the Allies launched five offensives
against Cassino's Benedictine monastery.
135 US Flying Fortresses reduced it to
rubble.
In the rubble and in command of the high
ground, the Germans repelled attempts by
Indian, Canadian, British, and New
Zealand formations.
Finally, General Alphonse Juin's Free
French, led by Moroccan irregulars
skilled in mountain warfare, opened the
way for the Polish Second Corps to carry
Monte Cassino.
On May the 17th, the Polish flag flew
above the ruins as the Germans finally
withdrew.
>> With my friend, I explore the area at
night
and we found Germans' helmets [music]
and with Germans' helmets, we pretended
to be Germans.
They are questioned and we would say,
"Jawohl."
And there were 12 cement bunkers with
one window each
from which they were shooting.
And we managed to disable them by
throwing grenades into the bunkers.
And that that's why we managed to
destroy them.
>> The Cassino front had taken the Allies 3
months for an advance of 15 km.
By late May, German divisions were being
badly mauled and Rome lay ahead.
Clark called for a drive east to
Valmonte to cut off the withdrawing
German 10th Army.
Mark Clark had other ideas, rather
imperial ideas.
His determination to be the liberator of
the eternal city allowed the 10th German
Army to withdraw intact.
June the 5th, Mark Clark led his forces
into Rome.
He failed to receive the publicity he
hoped for. The following day was D-Day.
It had taken the Allies 9 months to
advance from toe to knee at the cost of
40,000 Allied and 25,000 German
casualties.
The spring thaw that transformed [music]
the Eastern Front meant that the
Russians could begin their offensive and
on the 4th of March, they had moved.
But they advanced without one of their
best commanders. Nikolai Vatutin,
ambushed by partisans fighting for an
independent Ukraine, had died of his
wounds.
The strategic aim of the spring
offensive was to drive a wedge between
Army Group A and Army Group South.
>> At the moment, the best news comes from
the Russian front, where the Red Army
has been scoring one triumph after
another, beating back the invaders,
smashing their defenses.
>> In the first 2 days, Zhukov's first
Ukrainian front advanced 40 km despite
the clinging mud.
By the end of the month, Hitler had
sacked the commanders of both army
groups, von Kleist and von Manstein.
Walter Model and Ferdinand Schörner,
lesser commanders, but better Nazis,
were appointed to replace them.
On April the 8th, Soviet forces advanced
into the Crimea. In only 2 days, Odessa
fell.
On the 17th, Ternopil fell to Zhukov.
Not a well-known battle, not a major
city, but Hitler had declared Ternopil
to be a fortress.
A Führerfestung,
and the 4,500
man garrison defended it accordingly.
55 Germans survived the assault.
By mid-May, with [music] the surrender
of the final 25,000 troops, the Crimea
had been cleared and Soviet attention
turned to the summer.
To planning the greatest offensive of
the war,
Operation Bagration. [music]
Bagration was designed to coincide with
the invasion of Western Europe.
The second front that Stalin had been
promised would at last be opened in
1944.
>> Planning for the second front had been
underway since April 1943.
Hundreds and hundreds of men and women,
without the help of a single computer or
calculator or mobile telephone,
planned the logistics that would deliver
support, supply, and reinforce an
immense invasion force
shipped across 35 km of unpredictable
sea and landed on defended beaches.
Their work involved masses of men and
material and depended on secrecy.
All sorts of deceptions were employed.
The British Fourth Army in Scotland drew
German units north,
but there was no Fourth Army.
Patton's First Army, based in the
southeast, was a clear threat to the
Channel ports, but there was no First
American Army under Patton.
For every bomb dropped on Normandy,
three were dropped elsewhere.
The Germans were heavily dependent on
intelligence received from their agents
in the United Kingdom, but by D-Day,
every one of their agents had been
turned and was supplying Germany with
false information.
The greater part of the south coast
region of England to a depth of 16 km
[music] was declared a military zone.
Villages were evacuated and the invasion
was practiced.
Eisenhower, in supreme command, had an
Anglo-American team of meteorologists to
advise him, and they warned against the
5th of June, the original date, but gave
the go-ahead for the 6th. So, Eisenhower
gave the order for the invasion. It was
headed, "The tide has turned." "I hope
to God," Eisenhower said, "I know what
I'm doing."
>> We were just waiting, loading and
unloading,
when we started to load tanks,
is when we said, "Mhm,
uh this is it."
There wasn't anything mentioned as far
as uh
uh going for an invasion.
But, there was a lot of ships.
>> We didn't know much about it prior to
those few days before D-Day, except that
we knew we were going to invade France.
We had photographs of our
uh targets and on the beach in Juno and
all the rest of it.
>> It's the only thing we got to eat on the
way over, was this new stuff. A
shellfish soup.
Most men ate it so the bottom got red
hot and all those vegetables got burned,
and the top was cold. There's all sorts
of things that like that went wrong.
>> I was amazed at the efficiency of it
all.
We were told which number at landing
craft we would be on, so we would going
down hundreds and hundreds of vehicles.
Let's say they don't know you're on
landing craft 59. I don't know how about
that.
In fact, as as we got there, in comes
landing craft 59. It was quite
extraordinarily efficient.
>> The old outfit, they were around the
other way. They got them picketed in the
city.
I want to show all those boats. They're
ready to go.
I I learned machine we cannot lose.
>> Facing the invasion in overall command
was von Rundstedt. In command of the
forces opposing the landing Army Group B
was Erwin Rommel.
Though on D-Day itself, [music] Rommel
was absent on leave. It was his wife's
birthday.
There were 850,000
men in von Rundstedt's command, amongst
whom, choosing to fight as soldiers and
not die as prisoners, were 60,000
Russians.
The Germans had less tanks [music] for
the defense of France in 1944
than they had marshaled for its conquest
in 1940.
But they had the fortified Atlantic
Wall, which had been Hitler's idea
[music] and which extended over 2,000 km
and boasted 12,000 bunkers. [music]
2 million slave laborers had worked for
2 years to build the wall.
Much of its weaponry had been stripped
and shipped from the Maginot Line.
The invasion armada comprised 700
warships. Their role was both air
defense and shore bombardment.
2,700
ships supported the landing. They
carried the supplies, the
reinforcements, and the infrastructure
in the form [music] of fuel pipelines
and floating Mulberry harbors that would
make the landing sustainable.
And there [music] were 2 and 1/2
thousand landing craft.
Each of the ships' captains received a
book with 700 pages of instructions.
Above them,
the Allied Air Forces flew thousands of
aircraft.
The Germans could meet them with only
170 [music]
serviceable machines.
A total of 3 million Allied personnel
were involved in the effort.
>> 5,000 ships all gathering together to
make the invasion [music] into Normandy.
It was a sight to see.
You know, on a horizon seeing all these
ships, they looked like little dots
getting bigger and bigger and then
merging into Normandy beach.
>> Everybody who was there will say
the ships, the aircraft,
but one would never have ever forgotten.
>> Going across in the convoy,
there were so many landing craft.
Sailors were all talking to each other
by semaphore, just using their arms.
They were all so close together they
could talk to other craft.
It was very rough.
There was no cover in the landing craft.
You're just lying on the deck.
I was extremely sick and spent most of
the time praying that the Germans would
come and sink us.
>> I spent the night in my bunk.
It was obviously going to be a busy day
ahead.
>> The invaders landed on a 90-km plus
stretch of five beaches along the
Normandy coast. The names given to those
beaches by the planners are an [music]
indestructible part of the history of
the war.
The 21st Army Group, General Montgomery,
sailed from ports along the British
coast.
The US First Army, General Bradley,
landing on Utah and Omaha beaches.
The British Second Army, General
Dempsey, landing on Gold, Juno, and
Sword.
The US 82nd and 101st Airborne landed
behind Utah, the British 6th Airborne
behind Sword.
It was calculated that all of the
airborne troops dropped on the night of
June 5th-6th, up to 75%
landing at the wrong locations, took no
part in the early fighting.
Rommel had 34 divisions opposing the
landing. Many were facing the wrong way.
Most were [music] under strength and
some were feeble units comprising
exclusively men with stomach complaints.
Five Allied divisions [music] came
ashore.
The first, the US 4th Infantry Division,
landed 1,800 m from its target due to a
strong current, but that swept it to a
weakly defended position.
The 4th landed 23,000 men on D-Day and
took only [music] 197
casualties.
It was a different [music] story on
Omaha.
>> We couldn't hit
Beach in its entirety.
So, we had to lower the ramp
as much as we can, and everybody had to
go into the water.
A lot of the people with gear
went down, and some of them perished
because of the gear.
>> Omaha Beach was dominated by cliffs from
which, for much of the day, the US 1st
and 29th divisions were pinned by
intense fire.
The swimming tanks had been launched
prematurely, and many founded, leaving
the infantry without cover.
By day's end, 55,000 had been landed,
but at a cost of more than 4,600 [music]
casualties.
The third beach, left to right, was
Gold,
where the British 50th Division landed,
supported by 8th Armoured Brigade.
>> I got to water chest deep,
and I got out of water onto the sand.
And I'd only gone about three or four
paces,
one of us two went down
alongside me,
and the blood was spurting out.
I went out and come on, Charlie, come
on.
Somebody screamed out,
"Get off the beach, get off the beach."
He's not to tell me.
I was on my on my way anyway.
But you can't just leave your mate.
>> 3rd Canadian Division landed on Juno,
where it met particular difficulty with
underwater obstacles and rough water.
By nightfall, it had made contact with
the British 50th on its right.
The final beach was Sword,
where the British 3rd Division landed
successfully.
>> I'm not sure about that. There were a
navy chap standing there directing
everybody off the beach.
Get off.
Get off. Off the beach. Off you go.
There was one of them and he's looking
at his shoulder
in a stupid sort of way, you know.
There were bits of his arm flying off as
the bullets went in them.
He was taking a full burst in his
shoulder and he was just looking at it.
God knows how many men they lost in that
way.
>> The perhaps inevitable general
confusion, the mass of men and machines,
and the contrasting [music] levels of
success
created an opportunity for the
defenders, initially wrong-footed and
slow [music] to respond, to redeploy.
The 21st [music] Panzer Division took a
firm grip on Caen, denying it to the
Allies for whom it had been a D-Day
objective.
They continued [music] to defend the
town for some time.
>> The first job was to take the blockhouse
opposite the the British.
And then we crossed the minefield.
That minefield, you know, was seven
tanks going all the way to land with us.
>> We'd been given three tanks just for the
landing to cut the wire.
They lasted 5 minutes, I believe.
And one after the other
bang bang
bang.
We hit.
>> The Germans had the 88s and the 88s were
tremendous
weapon.
>> As June 6th wore on, new units began to
extend the perimeter away from the
beaches, short of the proposed target
line, but beginning to move into the
villages on or behind the coast.
>> Get off the beaches fast as you can.
And turn right at the little road that
you come across.
And eventually you'll see the church.
And make your own way there through the
streets.
So I went up to the door. I took the
cord for a 5-hour and I aimed at the
lock, John Wayne fashion, bang.
As soon as I fired that shot
there was a tap on my shoulder.
And I turned around and there's this man
dressed in black, Irish priest. He's
shaking his head.
And he walks over to it, just turns it
off.
And I walked in there as humble as
anything, but
I was completely and utterly humiliated.
A big roughy-chuffy commando, God love
me, too.
>> It was late afternoon before Hitler gave
permission for the deployment of two
Panzer divisions that had been held in
reserve.
The end of June the 6th, he was still
not fully convinced that the Normandy
landing was the real invasion rather
than a faint.
But, it was no faint.
>> This is France.
>> By the end of the first day, the allies
were short of their target line along
almost the whole length of the invasion,
but they had 156,000
men ashore, established ashore,
supported ashore. They had control of
the sky, naval support was unchallenged,
meaning that reinforcement and resupply
would be unhindered.
It had not been a walk in the park.
In only 3 weeks, the allies would land
[music] 800,000 troops. They would break
out from Normandy and begin to roll back
the German conquests.